OMAR ABID

Machine Learning Engineer

InkedIn.com/in/omarabid4/ ♥ github.com/omarabid59 ♥ omar-abid.ca
C: +1 647 701 5856 | omar.abid4@gmail.com
Toronto, Ontario

HIGHLIGHTS

As a Machine Learning Engineer, I am experienced with statistical data analytics, big data processing, feature engineering and building Machine Learning models for production environments. Worked with Computer Vision, NLP and structured data. Interested in the aviation, health and finance sectors.

Experience	Description
4 years	Designing, building and deploying Machine Learning models in a production environment
4 years	2D and 3D computer vision algorithms for object detection, tracking and mapping
3 years	Software development, version control, unit testing and CI/CD
4 vears	Research methods, statistics, physics, biology, technical writing and teaching

EDUCATION

Year	Degree & Institution
2018	MSc, Computer Science & Engineering. Specialization in Machine Learning and Computer Vision, York University
2014	Honors BSc, Biophysics, York University

SKILLS & KNOWLEDGE

SITILLS & ITINO	WEEDGE
Languages	C/C++, Python, Java, Bash, SQL
Machine Learning	Neural Networks, SVMs, kNNs, Logistic Regression, Autoencoders
Cloud Services	GCP, AWS, Azure
Libraries	Tensorflow, Keras, PyTorch, Pandas, OpenCV, Spark, Hadoop
Computer Vision	OCR, 2D object detection, segmentation and tracking. 3D object detection with SfM & SLAM
Modeling	Deep learning, CNNs, LSTM RNNs, supervised and unsupervised classification

EXPERIENCE

2019 - Present	Machine Learning Engineer at Curate Mobile Ltd (Toronto, ON) Developed machine learning algorithms to optimize profit margins on real time bidding platforms for the advertisement industry.
2018	Machine Learning Contractor at Sylphia Consulting (Toronto, ON) Designed and implemented a machine learning pipeline for non-invasively measuring hemoglobin levels using computer vision on biomedical images.
2018 – 2019	Machine Learning and Computer Vision Engineer at Watopedia (DIFC, Dubai, U.A.E)

the transportation sector [Projects 1 - 3].

Designed and implemented large scale machine learning models to identify security threats in

· Deployed software to Google Cloud leading to substantial gains in investment capital

2016 – 2017 Teaching Assistant at York University (Toronto, ON)

Invigilated and graded exams and labs for first to third year undergraduate computer science students. Worked with robotics, mobile app development and software design. Directed the labs and office hours for the following courses:

- Fall 2016 | EECS 1011: Computational Thinking Through Mechatronics
- Winter 2016 | EECS 1570: Introduction to Computing for Psychology
- Winter 2016 | EECS 3311: Software Design
- Summer 2016 | EECS 3301: Programming Language Fundamentals

2015 - 2018 **Computer Vision Researcher at York University (Toronto, ON)**

Improved the efficiency and eliminated bugs on a proprietary neural network simulator implemented in C++ resulting in a more stable system for experimental research purposes

2013 – 2014 Research Assistant at York University (Toronto, ON)

- Hardware Engineer (10/2013 04/2014): Engineered an electronic circuit for reliable measurement of biological cell electric potentials
- Data Analyst (04/2013 08/2014): Statistical data analysis of EEG of Macaque Monkeys for neural population decoding [Project 4]
- Data Analyst (10/2013 08/2014): Statistical data analysis of human behavioral data to infer differences in learning strategies among patients.

SIGNIFICANT PROJECTS

Ad CTR Engine

Big data preprocessing with Apache Spark, feature engineering and building a model for predicting the Click Through Rate (CTR) on an Ad with TensorFlow models. Models served in a production environment with TensorFlow serving.

Obiect Detection & Tracking

Real time object detection and notification of threats (suspicious behaviors and objects of interest) in security critical environments using **Deep Neural Networks**. Improved effectiveness of clients by allowing quick searching of surveillance video by object type, color, location or time. [Project 1]

Recognition

Face recognition pipeline in Python using Tensorflow. Resulted in a state-of-the art system that provided real-time security deployment to company clients. Also engineered an algorithm to add new, previously unseen faces to the **SQL** database for seamlessly updating identities. [Project 2]

Cloud ML model Deployment

Machine Learning on the cloud with Google Cloud Platform for object detection with WebRTC, built in Python. [See GitHub]

Data processing pipeline

A pipeline for collecting, cleaning and augmenting large datasets. Maintained software packages with git resulting in rapid development of machine learning models. [Project 3]

Neural decoding

Analyzed EEG data of Macaque monkeys using MATLAB's Statistics and Machine Learning Toolbox. An population SVM model was developed that indicated differences in EEG activations under different task conditions leading to key research insights for future work in the lab. [Project 6]

ACTIVITIES

Finalist Selected as a NextAl 2018 finalist – An entrepreneurial program for startups in Al. (2018)

Startups Started Fix My Tech Now – A company providing hardware and software repairs for laptops, computers and mobile devices. (2014 - 2015)

Nomination MSc Thesis Nominated for Best Thesis Award (2018)

Volunteer Scotiabank Buskerfest for Raising Awareness of Epilepsy (2014), Dog Shelter Volunteer (2018)

RELEVANT COURSES

Master's Level Data Mining, Advanced Topics in Computer Vision, Distributed Computing

Bachelor's Level Multivariate and vector calculus, linear algebra, experimental physics with data analysis, statistics,

Design and Analysis of Algorithms, Software Design, Data Structures

Coursera Data Engineering on Google Cloud Platform, Recommendation Systems with TensorFlow on Google Specialization Cloud Platform

PUBLICATIONS

- 2019 Master's Thesis: Cognitive Programs Memory: A framework for integrating control in STAR, York University
- Sengupta, R., Abid, O., Bachoo, A., & Tsotsos, J. (2017). Attentional blink as a product of attentional control signals: A computational investigation. Journal of Vision, 17(10), 1197-1197.